Guide to the New York University Archives Collection on Faculty and Alumni Memory Projects MC.226
New York University Archives
New York University Archives Collection on Faculty and Alumni Memory Projects
1884, 1912-1990
1963-1978
New York University Archives
MC.226
3.50 Linear Feet in 5 manuscript boxes, 2 cassette boxes, and 2 items in a shared cassette box.
74 audiocassettes
This collection consists of written and audio recorded memories of New York University (NYU) and Washington Square College professors, staff, and alumni which were carried out during the 1960s through the 1980s and collected under the auspices of the University Archives. These accounts were initially coordinated by NYU's Vice President and Secretary Thomas Pollack and later by Bayrd Still, historian and founding Director of the University Archives. A similar, connected project was carried out by former NYU student and writer Brian Huggins. The New York University Archives Collection on Faculty and Alumni Memory Projects (dated 1884-1990, bulk 1963-1978) includes audio recordings and letters written by University faculty, staff, and alumni describing their experiences at New York University and Washington Square College. The letters were sent to the University beginning in 1963, and later in the 1960s and early 1970s expanded into oral history interviews with the intent of preserving memories of those who were important to the history of the University in the 20th century. Interviewees include alumni, faculty, and administrators of the University such as James W. Armsey, Miguel de Capriles, Lucy Chamberlain, and James M. Hester. This collection also includes project proposals, audio recordings, correspondence, and notes related to a complementary off-shoot project on the experiences of University students conducted by Brian Huggins in 1977-1978. This project intended to document the student experience at the University during the early to mid-20th century. These interviews were intended to be resources for a book on student life for the sesquicentennial anniversary of the University. This project was not completed as originally conceived.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Appraisal
The following were separated from the collection: Memoirs and reminiscences of the late Prof. George Bush (1860); NYU's Stern School of Business: A Centennial Retrospective (1995); and a group of folders containing basic/publicly available information on high-profile NYU donors and their related campus building projects.
Three interviewee release forms were identified (Mary Siegel, Lillian Hornstein, and Ellen Marie Barrett), removed from the collection, and returned to the curator to be stored in the collection file.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into three series. Within each series, files are arranged alphabetically by subject's last name.
Series I. Faculty Memories Project
Series II. University Oral History Project and Related Materials
Series III. Brian Huggins Undergraduate Student Life in Washington Square Project
Historical Note
The New York University Archives has collected documentation of multiple interrelated projects carried out in the early 1960s through the 1980s focused on recording the remembrances of NYU and Washington Square College professors, staff, and alumni about their experiences during the early to mid-20th century.
NYU's Vice President and Secretary Thomas Pollack initiated a project to gather remembrances and stories specifically about Washington Square College departments through their professors and general staff. These recollections were initially requested in 1963 through New York University publications.
In the late 1960s to the 1980s Bayrd Still, Director of the University's Archive Office conducted interviews with the intent of documenting memories of those who worked at and attended the University during the 20th century. The University worked closely with the Columbia University Oral History Program on this project.
In the late 1970s, an off-shoot of this project was conducted by Brian Huggins, a former NYU student and writer. After Huggins received positive responses to articles he wrote about NYU student experiences during the early 20th century he decided to write a history of NYU undergraduate student life, to be published during the University's sesquicentennial anniversary.
Custodial History
This collection was created by NYU University Archives Staff, who grouped the files due to their connections to each other, and more than likely began storing them together starting in the 1980s. Brian Huggins was involved in the early oral history project and his proceeding project in the late 1970s was encouraged and supported by Bayrd Still, Director of the University Archives.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Audiovisual materials that have not been preserved may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact the New York University Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Scope and Contents
The New York University Archives Collection on Faculty and Alumni Memory Projects (dated 1884-1990, bulk 1963-1978) includes written accounts and oral history interviews from University faculty and alumni describing their experiences within various departments at New York University (NYU) and Washington Square College during the early to mid-20th century. A 1963 project initiated by NYU's Vice President and Secretary Thomas Pollack gathered remembrances and stories of Washington Square College departments through letters sent from professors and general staff. This collection also contains recorded oral history interviews and related written material from faculty and administrators dating from the late 1960s to the 1980s which were coordinated by Bayrd Still, Director of the University Archive Office, who was also one of the primary interviewers. Talking points of these interviews include department and school histories and their faculty; interactions between professors; student life experiences; clubs; atheletics; experiences of female professors and students; and reflections on historical events such as world wars and the Great Depression of the 1930s. These interviews are in the form of audio recordings and transcripts, as well as interview questions, notes, and correspondence.
This collection also contains material related to a project conducted by Brian Huggins on the undergraduate student life experience at NYU. Audio recordings in this collection include alumni interviews dating from 1977 to 1978 containing remembrances from the Classes of 1909 to 1942. Additionally, the collection contains correspondence, project proposals, and work notes.
Oral history.; Audiocassettes.; Transcripts.; Universities and Colleges -- Faculty.; Universities and Colleges -- Administration; College students -- New York (N.Y.); New York University; Huggins, Brian; Pollock, Thomas Clark, 1902-1988; Still, Bayrd
- Series I. Faculty Memories Project, 1884, 1912-1982; 1 linear foot in 2 manuscript boxes
  Historical Note
  In 1963, the University's Vice President and Secretary Thomas Pollack initiated a project with the intent of writing a modern history of New York University and the Washington Square College. Notices were placed in a University publication encouraging faculty and alumni, as well as administrative and support staff within the various University departments and schools to send letters which included their reminiscences.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains letters dating from 1963 to the early 1970s which convey the experiences of Washington Square College and later New York University faculty and staff during the 1920s through 1940s. These letters include histories of various departments and schools; interactions between faculty; facilities staff stories on how they came to work at the College or University; experiences of female faculty and students; the history of University clubs and programs; and memorable student experiences. This series also contains materials dated earlier than this project, which were added to the files most likely due to their similar nature. These items include material dating from the mid-1800s to the 1950s, such as publications containing faculty memories, printed speeches, and an independently researched and written memoir of the history of the Washington Square Journal.
  - List of Project Participants, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abbott, Edward, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Abbott, Lyman, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Adkins, Nelson F., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Arnold, Arthur, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Atkins, Willard E., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Austern, Thomas, 1952, 1954, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ayearst, Morley, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Baltzly, Alexander, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Barr, Jean B., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bauer, Charles, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Benz, Margaret, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Berger, Dorothea, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bower, Warren, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Cargill, Oscar, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Carpenter, Bruce, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Crossman, Arthur, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cutajar, Paul, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Davidson, Irwin D., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Denmark, Bernhardt, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Eaton, Myrwyn, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Edison, Beatrice, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Ehret, William F., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Ehrlich, Otto H., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Ellis, Brooks F., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Emerson, Robert S., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Falk, Minna R., circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Falnes, Oscar, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Ferguson, Walter, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Gamzue, Boris, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Gerstenberg, Charles W., circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Gibson, William M., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Graham, Palmer, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Grisewood, Edgar, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Gustov, Alice, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Hagstrom, Edwinna, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Hanna, Joseph, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Hodenpyl, Margaret T., 1931 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Hook, Sidney, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Hulme, Harold, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - John, Wallace, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Johnson, Claus, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Johnson, Jotham, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Kirschenbaum, Armand R., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Klemin, Alexander, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Kline, Morris, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Komarek, Viola, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Lehon, Hyman, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Lind, Ilse, 1963, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Lovett, Gabriel, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - MacDonald, Lois, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Maire, Raymond, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Marden, W.M., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Marin, William Peyton, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Marsland, Douglas, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Mateyko, Gladys M., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - McCullough, Bruce, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - McLeod, Stuart C., 1943 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Medical Center -- Questionnaires, Respondent Lists, and Letters, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Middlebrook, Ruth, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Nicastro, Albert, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Noss, Henry, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Oppenheim, Jack N., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Oppenheim, Marion Weil, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Park, Joseph H., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Perry, Robert, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Pritchard, Norman H., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Putney, Taylor, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Reighard, Catherine, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Rose, Ernst, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Schweizer, Malvina, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Shamos, Morris H., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Spock, Leslie E., 1963 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Stein, Bruno, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Stevenson, J.J., 1912, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Swenson, Rinehart J., 1963 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Swift, Richard, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Tashjian, Nouvart, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Tompkins, Leslie J., 1945 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Vance, John, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Voorhis, Harold O., 1950, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Wahlert, Howard, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Wald, George, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Waldman, Martin G., 1963 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Washington Square College Newspapers -- History, 1968-1980 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
- Series II. University Oral History Project and Related Materials, 1967-1990; 3 Linear Feet in 4 manuscript boxes and two cassette boxes; 40 audiocassettes
  This series contains audio recordings and transcripts of University Archive Office-sponsored interviews from faculty and administrators dating from the late 1960s to the early 1980s as well as correspondence, question lists, and project notes. Interview topics include the the establishment of various University departments and schools and their faculty, including the Courant Institute of Mathmatical Sciences; Department of Music and Performing Arts; NYU School of Law; the Graduate School of Social Work; and the Sociology and Anthropology Departments.
  The University Archive Office conducted oral history interviews during the late 1960s to the 1980s by various interviewers, including University Archive Office Director Bayrd Still, who was the primary contact for the project. The interviews were intended to document memories of the University during the 20th century through its faculty, alumni, and staff. The University Archive worked closely with the Columbia University Oral History Program on this project, with Columbia University providing transcription services for many of the interview recordings.
  - Armsey, James, March 10, 1976
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0001)
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0002)
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0003)
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0004)
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0005)
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0006)
    - Transcript, Correspondence, Notes (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Baldwin, Marshall, 1972
    - Original Recording, January 14, 1972 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0007)
    - Transcript, Notes (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Baltzly, Alexander, 1976-1978
    - Original Recording, May 3, 1978 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0008)
    - Original Recording, May 3, 1978 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0009)
    - Transcript, Correspondence, Notes (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Barrett, Ellen Marie, November 1981
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0010)
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0011)
    - Transcript (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Baumol, William -- Article, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Bender, Thomas -- Transcript, Article, 1976, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Bernstein, Martin, February 26, 1980
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0012)
    - Transcript (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bierstedt, Robert -- Correspondence, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Bischoff, Ralph, June 11, 1968
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0013)
    - Transcript, Correspondence, Notes (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Borowitz, Sidney, March 1, 1979
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0014)
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0015)
    - Transcript, Correspondence, Notes (Box 3, Folder 3-5)
  - Brown, Margaret, 1976-1989
    - Original Recording, November 15, 1983 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0016)
    - Original Recording, November 15, 1983 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0017)
    - Original Recording, November 15, 1983 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0018)
    - Transcript, Correspondence, Notes (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Chamberlain, Lucy, 1967-1970
    - Original Recording, December 7, 1967 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0019)
    - Original Recording, July 25, 1968 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0020)
    - Transcript, Correspondence, Notes (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Cooley, Hollis -- Correspondence, Notes, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Craven, W. Frank -- Correspondence, Notes, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Cuneo, Mathilda -- Original Recording, March 21, 1981; cuid18726 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0021)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Duration: 87 minutes
  - Davenport, Harry -- Notes, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - de Capriles, Miguel, 1972-1982
    - Original Recording, May 11, 1976 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0022)
    - Original Recording, May 11, 1976 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0023)
    - Original Recording, May 11, 1976 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0024)
    - Original Recording, May 11, 1976 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0025)
    - Original Recording, May 11, 1976 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0026)
    - Original Recording, May 11, 1976 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0027)
    - Transcript, Correspondence, Notes (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Denonn, Lester E. -- Correspondence, Notes, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Drake, Ormond J. -- Correspondence, Notes, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Epstein, Harry -- Article, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Fisher, Jacob -- Correspondence, Biographical Sketch, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Group Recollections, Class of 1932, February 4, 1978
    - Tape One -- Bayard Still, cuid18727 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0028)
      Duration: 5 minutes
      Static heard in content; Side 2 is blank
    - Tape Two -- Bayard Still, cuid18730 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0029)
      Duration: 64 minutes
  - Harvey, Ray, November 21, 1967
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0030)
    - Transcript, Correspondence (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Hester, James M., 1974-1975
    - Original Recording, February 5, 1975 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0031)
    - Original Recording, February 5, 1975 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0032)
    - Transcript, Correspondence, Notes (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Huggins, Brian, January 15, 1979
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0033)
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0034)
    - Transcript, Correspondence, Notes (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Kelly, Harry -- Correspondence, Notes, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Korff, S.A. (Serge) -- Notes, Autobiography Manuscript, circa 1970s (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
  - Masson, Henry J. -- Correspondence, Notes, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Mitchell, Ed -- Correspondence, Notes, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Park, Joseph H. -- Correspondence, Notes, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Rabkin, Jacob, May 7, 1980
    - Original Recording (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0035)
    - Transcript (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Roberto, Joseph, 1967-1968
    - Original Recording, July 25, 1968 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0019)
    - Transcript, Notes (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Russos, George -- Original Recording, November 22, 1985 (Box 6, Audiocassette 226_0036)
  - Schiff, John M. -- Speech Script, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Schwartz, Gertrude -- Original Recording, December 10, 1980; cuid18728 (Box 7, Audiocassette 226_0037)
    Duration: 96 minutes
  - Simon, Caroline -- Original Recording, January 30, 1981 (Box 7, Audiocassette 226_0038)
  - Smith, E.C. -- Correspondence, Notes, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Stoddard, Gertrude -- Original Recording, March 15, 1968 (Box 7, Audiocassette 226_0039)
  - Taylor, William -- Original Recording, May 27, 1980 (Box 7, Audiocassette 226_0041)
  - Wellman, Warner -- Correspondence, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Widman, Michael -- Original Recording, December 2, 1981 (Box 7, Audiocassette 226_0040)
  - Wolfe, Thomas -- Notes, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Woolwich, Masha -- Notes, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Series III. Brian Huggins Undergraduate Student Life in Washington Square Project, 1977-1979; 1.50 Linear Feet 1 manuscript box, 1 cassette box, and 2 items in a shared cassette box; 34 audiocassette
  Brian Huggins, a former New York University student (class of 1978) and feature editor for the Washington Square News, organized a project from 1977 to 1978 to gather oral history interviews from alumni and write a book on the experience of the University's undergraduate students during the early part of the 20th century. Huggins had previously written well-received articles on the experiences of NYU students which inspired him to write a book. Huggins received a $1,000 grant from the Office of Student Affairs and obtained a recommendation from the University Archives Office, encouraging funders to support the project. The plan was to interview a large selection of University alumni, using the information to write the book and then and publish it during the University's sesquicentennial anniversary, but the project was never completed as originally conceived.
  This series contains audio recordings of alumni and faculty interviews conducted by Brian Huggins from 1977 to 1978. These interviews include stories about students' fashion; fraternity life; experiences of female law students; students use of Washington Square Park; the influx of military veterans into classes after World War II; experiences of Jewish and Catholic students at the University Heights campus; and athletic team activities and events. The interviewee's memories are not only shared through the lens of a university student, but also their experience as New York City area residents during key events in United States history during the early to mid-20th century including Prohibition during the 1920s; the 1929 financial crash, followed by the Great Depression of the 1930s; exposure to music and theater; and also urban and youth cultural issues that marked the 1950s and 1960s. The series also contains Huggin's project proposal, correspondence, book chapter samples, interview summary notes, and a small number of interview transcripts from the audio recordings.
  - Project Proposal, Correspondence, Notes, Book Outline, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 4-7)
  - Anonymous Woman Alumna, December 10, 1977
    - Original Recording (Box 7, Audiocassette 226_0042)
    - Notes (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Baudin, Maurice, 1977-1978
    - Original Recording, December 2, 1977 (Box 7, Audiocassette 226_0043)
    - Original Recording, December 2, 1977 (Box 7, Audiocassette 226_0044)
    - Notes (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Benton, Paul, October 17, 1977
    - Original Recording (Box 7, Audiocassette 226_0045)
    - Original Recording (Box 7, Audiocassette 226_0046)
    - Original Recording (Box 7, Audiocassette 226_0047)
  - Bloustein, Oscar, December 9, 1977
    - Original Recording (Box 7, Audiocassette 226_0048)
    - Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Digangi, Charles, December 12, 1977
    - Original Recording (Box 7, Audiocassette 226_0049)
    - Correspondence, Notes (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Ehmann, W. Howard, September 19, 1977
    - Original Recording (Box 7, Audiocassette 226_0052)
    - Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Epstein, Harry, October 13, 1977
    - Original Recording (Box 7, Audiocassette 226_0050)
    - Notes (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Hirschhorn, Herbert, September 28, 1977
    - Original Recording (Box 7, Audiocassette 226_0051)
    - Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Jarvis, N. Leonard -- Telephone Interview Responses, circa 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Karlin, Margaret Fuller, 1977-1978
    - Original Recording, January 13, 1978; cuid18729 (Box 7, Audiocassette 226_0053)
      Duration: 55 minutes
    - Correspondence, Notes (Box 5, Folder 16)